[Music]
hello and welcome to part nine of the
inventory tutorial series in this video
we're gonna be working on saving the
player inventory so you can see here if
i hit load the player hotbar now
fills back up with the inventory
the backpack has the inventory in it as
well
and if we go over to the chests we can
see that the chests have their inventory
stored as well which is what we did in
the last video so let's just get
straight into doing this okay so where
we left it off last time is that we
could walk around and pick up some
tomatoes and potatoes and then we could
go over to our chests and we could
access the inventory and we could put
our tomatoes in it well they were
potatoes but you know what i mean in our
tomatoes we can hit save come out
go back in and play and then if we load
the items that we'd picked up get
deleted
and then the potatoes and tomatoes are
still there but what we had left in our
player inventory uh wasn't getting saved
and that's what we're gonna work on in
this video okay so let's open up our
chest inventory
and you see in our chest inventory we
have this public struct the serializable
struct that we were using to save out in
our save data
and we'd save the inventory system as
well as a position and a rotation
and you see that this derives from
inventory holder
but so does our player inventory this is
uh
this inherits from inventory holder as
well and we need to save the same thing
we need to save this inventory system so
what i'm actually going to do is i'm
going to take this
script instead of calling it a chest
save data i'm going to just rename it to
inventory save data and i'm going to put
it onto the inventory holder parent
script so i'm just going to rename our
struct here
inventory
save data
and i'm going to cut this from our chest
inventory and i'm going to place it onto
our inventory holder script so
underneath the public class here let's
just
pop that there
so the good thing about this now the
inventory save data is for example you
may have other types of inventory holder
um you may have a mailbox that just
takes in mail you may have
you may have like a cauldron which is
technically an inventory holder but it
could only hold
like potions or something
and if each of these things are
placeable
and craftable in the world
then we can just use this public struct
inventory save data
and we can even use this for our uh
player's inventory as well but with the
player's inventory we don't need to care
about the position and rotation
necessarily because that will be
because that piece of save data would be
included in a different saving and
loading for like the player stat you'll
have a separate player save
system which will have its which will
have the player's position and rotation
like their location in the world uh
saved into that
and realistically you'd have their
inventory system probably saved into
that struct so you'd have a public
structure player save data and they'd
have their inventory system
position rotation
any stats that they've got on them
other stuff about like who they've
spoken to where they've been etc
um but just for the sake of this
tutorial i'm just going to keep it all
simple and we're going to have this one
struct which is what we save inventories
with so what i'm going to do is i'm
going to create another constructor that
doesn't care about position and rotation
so we can go
and start a public
inventory
save data so this is new constructor
and it's going to take in the inventory
system which we will call
in system
and here we can say that in system is
equal to underscore in system position
can just be set to vector 3 3.0
and rotation
can equal
quaternion dot identity
so then over on our player inventory um
file so we need to do what we did on the
chest inventory so we need to subscribe
to the load
unload game function in our awake method
and we should probably unsubscribe from
it in on destroy as well
then on over on our inventory holder uh
i'm going to implement a method called
load inventory which can take any save
data
but i'm actually going to make this
abstract so private
abstract void load inventory and we've
got an error here meaning that the class
isn't flagged as abstract so we need to
do a
public abstract class
which we've called inventory holder and
we can make this protected so it's a
protected abstract void load inventory
taking in some save data
on our chest inventory we just need to
do protected override void and the
reason that we're doing this instead of
having it just be a virtual void is that
on our chest we care about the position
and rotation on our inventory holder
we don't
so what i can do now is i can copy
this function from our chest inventory
and we can go over to our player
inventory holder so here we're going to
paste in our our load inventory
what we're going to do here is instead
of looking into a chest dictionary we're
going to say data dot
our player inventory
dot
inf system is not
equal to null
and we're just going to set our primary
inventory system to the
data
dot player inventory dot in system so
this pr player inventory is going to sit
on our save data script so we go over to
save data dot cs you can see this is
where we've got our string and our
serializable dictionary for our chest
dictionary
what we can actually do here is do a
public
inventory
save data and we'll call this player
and then in our constructor we'll have
to say player inventory is equal to a
new inventory save data okay so let's go
back over to our player inventory and
actually it's not called in system is
it's a
in system with a lowercase i that's my
mistake so we've called it in
system really because they're public
they should be
capital eyes were sticking to proper
naming conventions
okay
so
another thing that we're going to do
is we are going to
change
how the player inventory holder actually
works so you can see here we've got a um
secondary inventory system and this is
essentially our hot bar so it's the 10
slots that sit on the bottom of the
screen but that's just a bit clunky
because we'd have to keep track of the
players uh hotbar and their backpack
separately so that's just creating two
lots of data when there's not really a
need to do that so what we're actually
gonna do is we're to
get rid of the secondary inventory
system um just all together so we can
get rid of all of this i know it's
daunting deleting
lots of code so with that done we can
get rid of our awake function and
instead of this unity action here we're
going to say get rid of the
parameter and we're just going to call
on layer inventory changed so when we
load our save game we're going to call
this action so all we need to do there
is on play inventory changed we can call
this after we load in our inventory and
instead of this here so if keyboard.com
b key was pressed this frame we're going
to just swap this over to the on dynamic
inventory display requested action which
sits on the inventory holder script and
this is going to take in a
inventory system which is just going to
be our primary inventory system
and we're going to pass in an offset
so the offset for the player inventory
is going to be 10. so basically when we
call the on dynamic inventory display
requested panel we're not going to show
the first 10 items if the in the
inventory because they're going to be
the ones that are on our heart bar and
you can see that we're getting an error
here which means we
need to change something so back on our
inventory holder script where we've got
this on dynamic inventory display
requested we can also take in an int
which is the offset so
in system
to display
amount to offset display by
and because we don't have this uh
secondary inventory system anymore we
can get rid of this elsif and we can
just have this add to inventory and over
on our inventory system when we're
calling the on dynamic inventory display
requested we don't want an offset so we
can just uh pass in zero so now let's
jump over to our um ui script you can
see that the ui controller is having a
bit of a an issue because this backpack
action isn't a thing anymore and display
inventory
we can get rid of this method
and inventory to display needs to take
in an in offset and we need to pass this
offset through to the chest panel
refresh dynamic inventory i'm actually
going to just rename this to inventory
panel now because it can be a panel for
anything it doesn't have to be
just a panel for the chests so inventory
panel and i'm going to add formerly
serialized as so it doesn't lose its
reference
so you can see here it says formally
serialized as once we've recompiled the
editor we'll be able to remove that
um if you want to know more about that
click the link up in the top right
corner i did a video on on what this
does so
passing through our offset here we just
need to go to this uh
refresh dynamic inventory
function
uh method and actually implement the
offset mechanic
so here we're taking in um an
int
offset
and again we need to pass this along to
its
final destination
which is uh
this assigned slot method here so him to
display
offset
and that needs to take an int
our inventory because this is an
override we need to do the same on the
assign slot abstract method here so we
need to pass that inventory slot in
we need to pass that uh it offset into
that
and now instead of starting at zero we
can start at the offset so um i equals
offset
and then whilst the inventory display is
less than the inventory size we'll do
all of the other stuff so basically
we're missing
when we start to assign the slots if we
pass in
an inventory size of 50 because our
player inventory is a size of 50 10 of
which are for the hot bar
and we're passing in a offset of 10
it's going to skip the first 10 slots of
the inventory which i should be able to
show you
here so
that should all be working
it doesn't work it is there's something
wrong with our static inventory
and that's because we need to pass in
the offset here even though we don't use
it okay so that should
all be happy now so let's go back over
to unity that was a lot of changes
without testing any of them so hopefully
that will all work
let's recompile
no errors in the log
always a good sign
so i'm going to walk over to this
uh tomato
we've got our two potatoes
and they're coming into our hot bar
as we go over you'll see that
nothing happened and that's because we
probably forgot to do something
ah so our player imagery size was set to
10 because
we only had the hotbar and we got rid of
the secondary inventory system which is
our backpack so let's put this up to 50.
okay so that didn't work we got an error
and
that's because silly old me forgot to do
something on a static inventory display
class
you can see that we were looking for the
amount of slots and we put in 10
inventory slot uis
this is an array of the actual ui
inventory slots and we were checking its
length and making sure that it was the
same as our actual inventory size
and log in an error if it wasn't
just as a fail safe um but we need to
get rid of that now
and instead of doing int i equals zero
what we need to actually do is check i
say in equals zero and whilst i is less
than slots dot length
so there is a potential issue here and
if you decide to have um
say five inventory slots
you need to make sure you change that in
the code on the player inventory holder
where we're passing in this offset what
you may want to do is to have a public
is to have a serialized field
private in offset and we'll default that
to
and let's instead of hard coding that
there we'll just put in offset and we
can change this in the inspector if you
change the hotbar
so if we look at the player hotbar you
can see that we have 10 inventory slots
in the script so slots
10 that's these here
if you decide to only have five you just
need to make sure that you change that
on your player and the player offset
here
and actually if you wanted what you
could probably do is if we go over to
our player
inventory holder script
i'm actually going to put this offset
onto the inventory holder main class
so we'll do offset equals 10. let's make
this protected so we can access it from
our player inventory holder script
and i'm going to do a public int offset
a capital o
and this can be a property that returns
the offset field
so now over on our static inventory
display what we can say is instead of
slots.length we can actually check the
inventory
holder dot
offset
okay so with those changes done
we just want to go back over to our
player inventory holder cs script and
the last thing we need to do is in a
start function so private void start
we just want to add to the save game
manager
we want to get the data the player
inventory and we want to set a new
inventory save data just passing in our
inventory system
which is the primary inventory system
okay so back in the project
what you want to do is because we've
changed the way the save file is
actually set up and we've renamed some
stuff we just want to hit delete you
need to delete your old save file
which is important to get all of this
stuff right now in the prototyping phase
because obviously you'd hate for players
to have to delete their saves some games
do have that in early access do you need
to have save wipes and they get rid of
your saves
so that's just something to keep in mind
and that once you start changing the
structure of what's actually saved out
you can't then load that back in
or you can but you'd have to you know
code for that and convert stuff
um but let's just start walking over
these tomatoes here and these potatoes
here
so you can see that our hotbar got full
and as we go over the items on the
ground they start to fill up in the
backpack
we can go over to the chest and let's
put five tomatoes in here and some
potatoes
let's split that stack and put two in
there and one in there
and then let's hit save
let's come out go back in
let's load our game so we'll hit load
so all of the items were collected so
they're now not on there
over on this chest here we've got the
tomatoes and the potatoes that we put
away
in our backpack we've got them but you
can see our hot bar is missing
if we go over to our player
you can see on our actual inventory they
are there we we have those items but
they've not shown back up and that's
because the hotbar
unlike the dynamic inventory
it wasn't set to refresh when something
changed so when we load our save game we
just need to ask our hotbar to refresh
because obviously the data that's
contained within our player inventory
has changed
and that's quite simple if we go back to
the static inventory display class and
in
on enable
we can subscribe to player inventory
holder
dot
on player inventory changed
and let's make a method called refresh
static display
and let's just copy and paste that and
we'll change this to this
able
and we'll change that to on disable
and we'll unsubscribe
from that method
so in our refresh static display method
all we're going to do is take this out
of the start function
and we can get rid of that we don't need
to call base dot start
no
so we're going to take that out with our
start function we'll place it into the
refresh static display script
and then we can call refresh static
display from our start function
so back in unity if we hit play we
should just be able to load the game and
everything should now be working so
let's load you see that all the items
were picked up our player inventory
is all intact this is everything that we
had
we have our chests which have the
tomatoes and the potatoes in them
just as you would expect
so so i know uh code refactoring can
sometimes make for a little bit of a
hectic video i hope you all follow along
and it was okay in the next video we're
going to be doing a bit more refactoring
unfortunately and we're going to be
looking at the way references to items
within an inventory are stored so what i
mean by that is this is our save data
and you can see that the reference
to the actual item data
is we we store how many of the item we
have but the actual reference to the
data is this instance id
now you can see that if we build the
game
so here we are in the built version of
the game and if i hit load
you can see that the items get deleted
and that's because they have a unique id
it's not an instance id
that's an id that we've created and is
unique
um
but you can see none of our inventories
have any items in them and that's
because in a built version of the game
those instance ids change between the
built version and the editor version
and in patches down the line
they may change again if you upgrade
your engine or
you know sometimes just your project
will re-serialize and those instance ids
can change and that means that the
loading whether that's in editor or in a
built version of the game
would actually stop working and you'd
break player saves is a bit of an
oversight on my end um
but after this comment from 322 ss on
the previous chest inventory saving uh
they've kind of flagged this as an issue
i did a bit of researching and i've
found a way to fix that by creating an
item database using scriptable objects
so in the next video we'll take a look
at how to implement that fix it's very
simple but again it's just a little bit
of refactoring so that will be what
happens in the next video but in the
meantime i hope you're enjoying the
inventory tutorial series it's been very
good fun working on this if you'd like
the project files for this video or any
of the other videos in the series
you can head over to the patreon which
is linked in the description below
that's patreon.com forward slash dan
pass if you've struggled with anything
in this video or any of the videos so
far you can join the discord server
which again is linked in the description
below i'd be more than happy to help you
there but for now thanks for watching
and i'll see you in the next one bye
you